Guide to the William Evarts Benjamin Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
William Evarts Benjamin Papers,
1817-1940
Benjamin, William Everts, 1859-1940.
14 linear ft (ca. 4,000 items in 26 boxes & 4 volumes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079157
Biographical Note
Publisher, collector.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, documents, financial records, photographs, drawings, engravings, and printed materials of Benjamin. The personal and business papers concern Benjamin's publishing and bookselling company, his numerous benefactions, the disposal of his collections, and many printed catalogs for his company, 1883-1940. The two major correspondents are the business and financial records for the printing, binding, and extensive promotion through a network of agents of Stedman's A Library of Aamerican Literature from the Earliest Settlement to the Present Time; new ed. (New York, W.E. Benjamin, 1894). There are also letters, manuscripts, documents, and drawings of English literary figures collected by Benjamin. Among these are six letters of George Eliot, 47 letters and six manuscripts of John Ruskin, and three letters and one manuscript of Joseph Mallord Turner, with four letters relating to the artist. In addition there ten drawings and watercolors by Ruskin.
Also, 37 letters and one manuscript were removed from Benjamin's copy of Robert Langton's The Childhood and Youth of Charles Dickens and cataloged for this collection. One letter from Langton and 32 from others were addressed to Charles Roach Smith, a well-known antiquary of London. Several letters are concerned with numismatics (including two from John Stuart, Earl of Darnley, one each from William Henry Ashe, baron Heytesbury, and Chase Spence), but most of these letters relate to Charles Dickens: three letters from his son, Sir Henry Fielding Dickens, six from Henry Gardiner Adams, of the Mechanics' Institute of Chatham and Rochester, one each from Frederick William Fairholt, and Charles Stewart Montgomerie Lockhart, manuscript notes by John Gough Nichols, a letter from John Bowen Rowlands, one each from W.J. Taylor and Joseph Cotton Wigram, Bishop of Rochester, two from Humphrey Wood of the Mechanics' Institute, and of particular interest the two letters from Sampson Seaton, whose father was a friend of the father of the famous novelist. Many of these letters were written at the time of Dickens' death from people living in the area of Rochester and Chatham, his early childhood homes.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 7 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Catalogs
Series III: Business and Personal Papers
Series IV: Library of American Literature
Series V: Scrapbooks
Series VI: Photographs
Series VII: Printed Materials
Subjects
Mechanics' Institute of Chatham and Rochester.; Phelps, Charles Henry.; Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1833-1908.; Eliot, George, 1819-1880.; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900.; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851.; Langton, Robert.; Smith, Charles Roach, 1807-1890.; Darnley, John Stuart,--Earl of.; Ashe, William Henry.; Heytesbury,--Baron.; Spence, Chase.; Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870.; Dickens, Henry Fielding,--Sir.; Adams, Henry Gardiner.; Fairholt, F. W. (Frederick William), 1814-1866.; Lockhart, C. S. M. (Charles Stewart Montgomerie); Nichols, John Gough.; Rowlands, John Bowen.; Taylor, W. J.; Wigram, Joseph Cotton.; Wood, Humphrey.; Seaton, Sampson.; Publishers and publishing--New York (State)--New York.; Booksellers and bookselling--New York (State)--New York.; Authors, English.; Numismatics.; Paintings.; Photoprints.; Engravings.; Drawings.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
1943 M-43 Cartwright, Beatrice Benjamin and Henry Rogers Benjamin Gift
Alternate Formats
Royal Cortissoz and John Ruskin letters are on microfilm.
Gift of Beatrice Benjamin Cartwright & Henry Rogers Benjamin, 1943.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Abbott, Lyman (Box 1)
  - Adams, Henry Gardiner (Box 1)
  - Benjamin, William Evarts (Box 1)
  - Burke, John Bernard (Box 1)
  - Byron, Anne Isabella Noël (Box 1)
  - Campbell, Thomas (Box 1)
  - Carrington, Katherine S. Batts (Box 1)
  - Coleridge, Samuel Taylor (Box 1)
  - Coles, Jonathan Ackerman (Box 1)
  - Cirtisso, Royal (Box 1)
    [Available on microfilm]
  - Crockett, Samuel Rutherford (Box 1)
  - Cumberland, Richard (Box 1)
  - Darnley, John Stuart, 6th earl (Box 1)
  - Davis, Richard Harding (Box 1)
  - Dickens, Charles (Box 1)
  - Dickens, Dir Henry Fielding (Box 1)
  - Dix, Morgan (Box 1)
  - Dumas, Alexander, fils (Box 1)
  - Edgeworth, Maria (Box 1)
  - Eliot, George (Box 1)
  - Fairholt, Frederick William (Box 1)
  - Fawkes, Walter Ramsden (Box 1)
  - Gilbert, Thomas "Bishop of Shropshire" (Box 1)
  - Gilder, Jeannette L. (Box 1)
  - Goldwin, J. H. (Box 1)
  - Hale, Edward Everett (Box 1)
  - Hay, John (Box 1)
  - Heytesbury, William Henry Ashe, 2nd Baron (Box 1)
  - Homer, Winslow (Box 1)
  - Hubbard, Elbert (Box 1)
  - Hughes, Charles Evans (Box 1)
  - Ireland, Joseph N. (Box 1)
  - Jones, William Alfred (Box 1)
  - Kitton, Frederick George (Box 1)
  - Langton, Robert (Box 1)
  - Leigh, Oliver (Box 1)
  - Lockhart, Charles (Box 1)
  - Lockhart, Charles Stuart Montgomerie (Box 1)
  - Lubbock, Sir John, 1st Baron Avebury (Box 1)
  - Lupton, Thomas (Box 1)
  - Maas, Joseph (Box 1)
  - Mayer, Joseph (Box 1)
  - Mellon, Andrew W. (Box 1)
  - Mills, Ogden L. (Box 1)
  - Mitchell, Donald Grant (Box 1)
  - Moore, Thomas Sir (Box 1)
  - Nichols, John Gough (Box 1)
  - Overall, William Henry (Box 1)
  - Pearman, Augustus John (Box 1)
  - Phelps, Charles Henry (Box 1)
  - Purland, Theodosius (Box 1)
  - Rheade, Louis J. (Box 2)
  - Rockefeller, John D. (Box 2)
  - Rowlands, John Bowen (Box 2)
  - Ruskin, John (Box 2)
    [Also on microfilm]
  - Seaton, Sampson (Box 2)
  - Sheridan, Richard Brinsley (Box 2)
  - Smith, Charles Roach (Box 2)
  - Spence, Chas. (Box 2)
  - Stedman, Edmund C. (Box 3)
  - Symons, Arthur (Box 3)
  - Taylor, W. J. (Box 3)
  - Turner, Joseph Mallord William (Box 3)
  - Vanderbilt, George W. (Box 3)
  - Walcott, Mackenzie Edward Charles (Box 3)
  - Wigram, Joseph Cotton, Bishop of Rochester (Box 3)
  - Wilson, Harriett (Box 3)
  - Wood, Humprey (Box 3)
  - Wright, Thomas (Box 3)
  - Miscelleneous (Box 3)
- Series II: Catalogs
  - Duplicate File: Set No. 1 (Box 4)
  - Duplicate File: Set No. 2 (Box 5)
- Series III: Business & Personal Papers
  - American Antiquarian Society, Worcester, MA, 1927-1941 (Box 6)
  - American Historical Association, 1926/1927 (Box 6)
  - The Book Lover, 1888-1903 (Box 6)
  - Bookplates (Box 6)
  - Eastern High School, Washington, DC, 1930 (Box 7)
  - Engravings and illustrations (Box 7)
  - Government lists (Box 7)
  - Gutenberg Bible, 1891-1929 (Box 7)
  - Library of Congress, 1926-1929 (Box 7)
  - Library of Congress, 1930-1935 (Box 8)
  - Lyman Allyn Museum, New London, CT, 1935-1937 (Box 8)
  - Murillo's Imaculate Conception, 1926/1927 (Box 9)
  - Murillo's Imaculate Conception - Pallavicini Catalogue, 1927 (Box 9)
  - The New York Community Trust, 1926-1931 (Box 9)
  - The New York Historical Society, 1937-1939 (Box 9)
  - Photographs (Box 9)
  - Publishing business:advertising; bills, receipts, etc.; James Mcdonald, Bookbinder; print catalogue; printed materials; stock lists (Box 9)
  - Rogers, H.H. - condolences re. his death, 1909 (Box 10)
  - S.S. "H.H. Rogers" - launching, 1916 (Box 10)
  - Speyer property dispute, 1911-1913 (Box 10)
  - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation, 1927-1930 (Box 10)
  - Thatcher, John B. The Continent of America (Box 10)
  - Union College, 1890-1935 (Box 10)
  - Union College, 1936-1940 (Box 11)
  - University of Virginia, 1928-1930 (Box 11)
  - George Washington, 1889-1930 (Box 11)
  - Washington family, 1927-1930 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous: memoranda; notebook; clippings; pamphlet; title pages (Box 11)
- Series IV: Library of American Literature
  - Accounts, 1884-1903 (Box 12)
  - Accounts, 1903-1910 (Box 12)
  - Accounts - royalties (Box 12)
  - Advantages of the L.A.L. (Box 12)
  - Advertisements:; full page; 1/2 & 1/4 page; retailo, printed copy; written copy (Box 12)
  - Advertising (Box 12)
  - Advertising, sets exchanged for (Box 12)
  - Agents, (6 folders) (Box 13)
  - Agents - printed materials (Box 13)
  - Benjamin, Charles R. General Agent (Box 13)
  - Binding (Box 13)
  - Boston orders (Box 13)
  - Braunworth & Co. Bookbinders, (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Circulars (Box 13)
  - Colonial literature (Box 13)
  - Commendations, (10 folders) (Box 14)
  - Correspondence - miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - Courses of Reading, (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - Hovendon, John Relating to E.C. Stedman (Box 14)
  - Illustrations (Box 14)
  - Improvements in manufacturing (Box 15)
  - Jenkins & McCowan Printing (Box 15)
  - Legan matters (Box 15)
  - Macdonald, James Bookbinder (Box 15)
  - Portraits (Box 15)
  - Printed materials (Box 15)
  - Prospectus, etc., (3 folders) (Box 15)
  - Specimin pages (Box 15)
  - Stedman, Edmond Charles, (3 folders) (Box 15)
  - Webster & Co., (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
- Series V: Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook of clippings, 1884-1891, (1 volume) (Box 17)
  - Scrapbook (Box 28)
- Series VI: Photographs
  - Large photographs (Box 28)
- Series VII: Printed Materials
  For related materials on Library of American Literature see E.C. Stedman Papers
  - Books from W.E. Benjamin's library (Box 16)
  - The Collector (Box 18)
  - The Collector (Box 19)
  - The Collector (Box 20)
  - Catalogs 1-10 (Box 21)
  - Catalogs 11-29 (Box 21)
  - Catalogs 30-42 (Box 22)
  - Catalogs 43-53 (Box 22)
  - Catalogs 77-95 (Box 23)
  - Catalogs 13-66 (Box 23)
  - Catalogs 54-67 (Box 24)
  - Catalogs 68-76 (Box 24)
  - The Book Lover (Box 25)
  - The Book Lover (Box 26)
  - The Book Lover (Box 27)
  - The Book Lover (Box 28)
  - The Book Lover (Box 29)